A Guide to the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Administrative papers, 1897-1906
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Secretary of the Commonwealth, Administrative papers, 1897-1906
Library of Virginia
24960
1.75 cubic feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth on May 18, 1959.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth has evolved from early colonial times when there existed a Secretary of the Colony. Thomas Nelson held the position of the first Secretary of Virginia in 1776. Early Secretaries were elected by the public. An Act of the General Assembly in 1920 changed the election to a joint vote of the General Assembly. In a 1930 Act the duties of the Secretary were redefined with the Secretary of the Commonwealth serving as the ex officio secretary of the Governor, as custodian of many official State records, and as keeper of the Greater and Lesser Seals of the Commonwealth. The office of the Secretary has gradually acquired other functions, such as: service of out-of-state civil process; appointment and regulation of notaries public; and registration and oversight of lobbyists. The Office became a gubernational appointment subsequent to a 1958 Act of the Assembly. The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office.
The Secretary is appointed by the Governor for a term of four years. The Secretary has an Executive assistant and an Assistant who is in charge of prison mail and research duties. The Chief Clerk is responsible for the Governor's Journal and extraditions and acts as general office manager. Major activities are: serving as ex officio Secretary to the Governor; serving as the keeper of the seals of the Commonwealth; compiling and publishing the annual Blue Book; commissioning and regulating notary publics, including the publication of a Notary Handbook and conduct of disciplinary hearings; promulgating the lobbying disclosure requirements, registration of lobbyst, and recording of lobbying reports; servicing the civil process of out-of-state defendants and other parties; and authenticating and certifying the records of the courts and of any state agency.
Scope and Content Information
These records contain the general administrative papers from the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth. Included is general correspondence, gubernatorial proclamations, one pardon, and other materials. This collection has only a portion of the correspondence, as evidenced by much of the alphabet in the correspondents. The location of the other correspondence is unknown.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Each series is arranged alphabetically.
Organization
Organized into three series: Series I. General correspondence, 1900-1903; Series II. Gubenatorial Proclamations, 1903-1904; Series III. Other materials, 1897-1906.
Contents List
- Series I: General correspondence, 1900-1903
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - General correspondence: Bla, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General correspondence: Ble-Blo, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General correspondence: Blu-Bog, 1901-1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General correspondence: Boh-Bol, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General correspondence: Bom-Bor, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General correspondence: Bos-Boz, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General correspondence: Bra, 1901-1903 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General correspondence: Bre, 1900-1902 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General correspondence: Bri, 1901-1903 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General correspondence: Bro, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General correspondence: Brown, 1900-1902 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General correspondence: Bru-Bry, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General correspondence: Bua-Buc, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General correspondence: Bud-Bul, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General correspondence: Bum-Bur, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General correspondence: Bus-Buz, 1900-1902 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - General correspondence: By, 1902-1903 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General correspondence: Caa-Cam, 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General correspondence: Can-Car, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - General correspondence: Cas-Caz, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - General correspondence: Cea-Cez, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - General correspondence: Ch, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - General correspondence: Ci-Cl, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - General correspondence: Clark, Clarke, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - General correspondence: Coa-Cok, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - General correspondence: Col-Com, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - General correspondence: Con, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - General correspondence: Coo, 1901-1903 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - General correspondence: Cop-Cor, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - General correspondence: Cos-Coz, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - General correspondence: Cro, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General correspondence: Cua-Cum, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General correspondence: Cun-Cz, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General correspondence: Sm, 1901-1903 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General correspondence: Smith, A-Smith, D, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General correspondence: Smith, E-Smith, I, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General correspondence: Smith, J-Smith, N, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General correspondence: Smith, O-Smith, S, 1901-1903 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General correspondence: Smith, T-Smith, Z, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General correspondence: Sn, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - General correspondence: So, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General correspondence: Sp, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General correspondence: St (Saint), 1900-1902 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - General correspondence: Sta, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - General correspondence: Ste, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - General correspondence: Stevens-Stewart, 1900-1902 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - General correspondence: Sti-Sto, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - General correspondence: Str, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - General correspondence: Stu-Sty, 1900-1902 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - General correspondence: Su, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - General correspondence: Sw-Sz, 1901-1903 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - General correspondence: Taa-Tal, 1900-1902 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - General correspondence: Tam-Tax, 1901-1903 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - General correspondence: Tay, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - General correspondence: Te, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - General correspondence: Tho, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - General correspondence: Tia-Til, 1902-1903 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - General correspondence: Tim-Tiz, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - General correspondence: Toa-Tol, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - General correspondence: Tom-Toz, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - General correspondence: Tra-Tri, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - General correspondence: Tro-Tup, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - General correspondence: Tur-Tuz, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - General correspondence: Tw-Ty, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - General correspondence: Ua-Uz, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - General correspondence: Va-Vy, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Series II: Gubernatorial Proclamations, 1903-1904
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Quarantine Proclamation (Cattle), 1904 February 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Quarantine Proclamation (Cattle), Correspondence, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Thanksgiving Proclamation, 1903 November 11 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Woodward back to SC, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series III: Other materials, 1897-1906
  - Bond notices for notary publics, by jurisdiction, 1900-1904 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bond notices for state government employees, 1898-1906 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with state libraries regarding Virginia State Documents, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Pardons: William Kemp, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 3)